Register of the Poland Sluzba Bezpieczenstwa Departament III Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Poland Sluzba Bezpieczenstwa Departament III collection,
1925-1989
92053
33 manuscript boxes (13.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Underground pamphlets, leaflets, flyers, bulletins, photographs, video tapes, and miscellany, collected by Polish internal security police. Includes some reports and bulletins issued by Polish security police.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1992.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (36 reels).
Scope and Content Note
The Sluzba Bezpieczenstwa, Poland's security police, was created by the communist authorities in 1944 to deal with the anti-German and later also anti-Soviet underground operating in those parts of the country that had been "liberated" by the Red Army. It was known under different names but between the years 1956-1990, it operated under the name of Sluzba Bezpieczenstwa (better known as SB). It was established in the Ministry of the Interior (Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnetrznych) and remained the most loyal supporter of the Polish United Workers Party. For decades, besides strengthening the position of the communist authorities, it directed its efforts against any signs of social opposition, relying on a network of secret agents and collaborators who were responsible for numerous provocations.
The events of March 1968 (reflected in this collection) led the SB to operate on a larger scale than before, as the communists cleaned the party ranks of internal opponents. It also took more and more repressive measures against workers' revolts in 1970, 1976, and 1980-1981, when it radicalized its attitude toward the church and free labor unions. The SB fought against them unscrupulously, but unlike what happened in other East European communist countries, it accomplished less, as the magnitude of those movements made control impossible. In fact, it became more desperate, as exemplified by the murder of the priest Jerzy Popieluszko.
Most of this collection consists of the publications issued by the underground and political opposition of the late 1970s and 1980s, which, not surprisingly, the SB monitored with particular interest. There are also materials analyzing opposition views on such issues as the economy, the attitude toward communist initiatives, as well as domestic and foreign politics. Additionally, there are documents that shed light on the circumstances that led to the Round Table Talks between the communists and the opposition, initiated as they were by the head of the secret services, General Kiszczak.
The history of the SB in its formative years is described in the bulletins and monographs issued by the Ministry of the Interior, albeit in a distorted fashion - a perfect example of manipulation of the facts relating to the origins of communist control in Eastern Europe. The extreme brutality, for example, with which the population was treated in the 1940s and early 1950s, especially because of the involvement of the NKVD, had to be justified.
The records of the Sluzba Bezpieczenstwa do not contain personal files or correspondence. They consist of either duplicate copies of typescripts or mimeographs intended for internal distribution to various SB departments and local branches, or opposition underground publications that have since been in public circulation.
The collection was acquired by the Hoover Institution in the early 1990s, and supplements other collections in the Archives, particularly those of Solidarity activists and the collection entitled "Polish Independent Publications, 1976-1990."
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Internal security--Poland.; Subversive activities--Poland.; NSZZ "Solidarnosc" (Labor organization); Labor movement--Poland.; Labor unions--Poland.; Poland.; Communism.; Anti-communist movements--Poland.
Genres and Forms of Material
Video tapes.
Other Index Terms Related to this Collection
Poland. Sluzba Bezpieczenstwa. Departament III.
Series Description
- Subject File, 1939-1989. (Box 1-22)
  Bibliographic publications, bulletins, catalogs, clippings, leaflets, fliers, underground mimeographed materials, pamphlets, typescripts, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Miscellaneous Materials, 1981-1988. (Box 23)
  Banknotes, calendars, cartoons, fliers, miniature publications, phonotape cassette covers, postcards, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Postage Stamp Albums, 1980-1989. (Box 24-27)
  Postage stamps issued by the Underground in the 1980s in celebration of individuals and events
- Printed Matter, 1944-1988. (Box 27-32)
  Rare, internal circulation bulletins and mimeographed publications issued by security forces in communist Poland, arranged into bulletins and monographs, and therein alphabetically by title or subject
- Videotape Cassettes, 1980s. (Box 32)
  Two videotape cassettes issued by NSZZ "Solidarnosc" video services, covering social and political events in the 1980s
- Photographs, 1925-1988. (Box 33)
  282 prints depicting individuals and events relating to Poland's 20th century history, especially the 1980s
Container List
- SUBJECT FILE, 1939-1989 (Box 1)
  - Amnesty International - History, 1986 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Censorship - Poland (Folder 1: 2)
  - Demonstrations - Poland
    - 1968
      - Anniversary celebrations, 1981 (Folder 1: 3)
      - Official party line (Folder 1: 4-6)
      - Origin (Folder 1: 7)
    - 1989 - Calendar of events (Folder 1: 8)
  - Dissenters - Poland, 1945-1989 - Komandosi (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
  - Ecology - Poland (Folder 2: 3)
  - Elections - Poland
    - 1985 (Folder 2: 4)
    - 1989
      - Political parties (Folder 2: 5)
      - History of political opposition (Folder 2: 6)
      - Solidarity (Folder 2: 7)
  - Émigrés - Poland (Box 3)
    - General (Folder 3: 1)
    - Centers (Folder 3: 2-3)
    - Solidarity - Periodicals (Folder 3: 4)
    - Support for
      - Intellectual circles (Folder 3: 5)
      - Opposition (Folder 3: 6)
  - Government, Resistance to - Poland
    - 1981-1986 (Folder 3: 7)
    - 1984-1985 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Jews - Poland - 1968 (Folder 3: 9)
  - John Paul II, Pope - Trip to Poland, 1987 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Komitet Samoobrony Spolecznej KOR (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Kultura (Paris, France) (Folder 4: 2)
  - Martial law - Poland, 1981
    - General (Folder 4: 3)
    - NATO's position (Folder 4: 4)
    - Protests against, 1981-1982
      - General (Folder 4: 5)
      - Documentation (Folder 4: 6)
  - NSZZ "Solidarnosc" (Labor organization)
    - General (Folder 4: 7)
    - Congress, 1981 (Folder 4: 8)
    - Foreign offices, 1980-1989 (Box 5)
      - General
        - General (Folder 5: 1)
        - 1982-1985 (Folder 5: 2)
      - Structure, 1981-1984 (Folder 5: 3)
    - Political line
      - General (Folder 5: 4)
      - Martial law, 1981-1983 (Folder 5: 5)
    - Press agency (Folder 5: 6)
    - Propaganda (Box 6)
      - General
        - General
          - General (Folder 6: 1)
          - 1980-1981 (Folder 6: 2)
          - 1980-1986 (Folder 6: 3)
          - 1987 (Folder 6: 4)
        - Bydgoszcz (Folder 6: 5)
        - Podbeskidzie (Folder 6: 6)
        - Swietokrzyski region (Folder 6: 7)
        - Szczecin (Folder 6: 8)
        - Warszawa (Folder 6: 9)
      - Audiovisual forms
        - General, 1982-1986 (Folder 6: 10)
        - Audiocassettes (Folder 6: 11)
        - Radio (Folder 6: 12)
        - Video and satellite television (Folder 6: 13)
        - Video production (Box-folder 7: 1)
      - Medals and pins (Folder 7: 2)
      - Methods (Folder 7: 3)
      - Photography (Folder 7: 4)
      - Publishing activities, 1981-1983 (Folder 7: 5)
    - Protest action
      - General, 1981-1982 (Folder 7: 6)
      - Colleges and highschools, 1980-1981 (Folder 7: 7)
      - Lublin region, 1980 (Folder 7: 8)
    - Relations with Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnetrznych (Folder 7: 9)
    - Tymczasowa Komisja Koordynacyjna
      - 1985
        - Part 1 (Folder 7: 10)
        - Part 2 (Box-folder 8: 1)
      - 1982-1986 (Folder 8: 2)
  - Opposition (Political science)
    - Eastern Europe
      - General (Folder 8: 3)
      - Polish Underground's perspective (Folder 8: 4)
    - Poland
      - General
        - General
          - Part 1 (Folder 8: 5)
          - Part 2 (Folder 8: 6)
          - Part 3 (Box-folder 9: 1)
          - Part 4 (Folder 9: 2)
          - Part 5 (Folder 9: 3)
          - Part 6 (Folder 9: 4)
        - 1976-1985
          - General
            - Part 1 (Folder 9: 5)
            - Part 2 (Folder 9: 6)
            - Part 3 (Box-folder 10: 1)
          - Organizational chart (Folder 10: 2)
        - 1976-1986 (Folder 10: 3)
        - 1984-1986 (Folder 10: 4)
        - 1987 (Folder 10: 5)
      - Counter-revolutionary forces, 1980-1981 (Folder 10: 6)
      - Elections, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 11: 1)
      - Most wanted. Booklet distributed by the secret police, 1983 (Folder 11: 2)
      - Program
        - 1981-1986 (Folder 11: 3)
        - 1986 (Folder 11: 4)
        - 1987 (Folder 11: 5)
      - Propaganda
        - 1977-1981 (Folder 11: 6)
        - 1977-1985 (Folder 11: 7)
        - 1981-1987 (Folder 11: 8)
      - Referendum, 1987 (Folder 11: 9)
      - Reforms (Box 12)
        - General
          - 1987 (Folder 12: 1)
          - 1988 (Folder 12: 2)
        - Tactics (Folder 12: 3)
      - Solidarity's ally (Folder 12: 4)
      - Strategy, 1983 (Folder 12: 5)
      - Structure and description of major groups
        - 1976-1986 (Folder 12: 6)
        - 1989 (Folder 12: 7-8)
  - Pacifism – Poland (Box 13)
    - General
      - 1983-1986 (Folder 13: 1)
      - 1985 (Folder 13: 2)
      - 1986 (Folder 13: 3)
      - 1987 (Folder 13: 4)
    - Wojskowa Sluzba Wewnetrzna (Folder 13: 5)
  - Political activists - Poland
    - Grabski, Tadeusz (Folder 13: 6)
    - Hall, Aleksander (Folder 13: 7)
    - Jankowski, Henryk (Folder 13: 8)
    - Kuron, Jacek (Folder 13: 9)
    - Litynski, Jan (Folder 13: 10)
    - Michnik, Adam (Folder 13: 11)
  - Political parties - Poland
    - General - Centrist and right wing movements (Folder 14: 1)
    - Grupa Dialogowa Consensus (Folder 14: 2)
    - Komitet Obrony Robotnikow (Folder 14: 3)
    - Komitet Obrony Wiezionych za Przekonania
      - General (Folder 14: 4)
      - Origin (Folder 14: 5)
    - Komitet Oporu Spolecznego (Folder 14: 6)
    - Konfederacja Polski Niepodleglej
      - General (Folder 14: 7)
      - Communiqués (Folder 14: 8)
      - Program (Folder 14: 9)
    - Polska Partia Niepodleglosciowa (Box-folder 15: 1)
    - Ruch Mlodej Polski
      - 1976-1984 (Folder 15: 2)
      - 1976-1985 (Folder 15: 3)
    - Ruch Wolnych Demokratow (Folder 15: 4-5)
    - Solidarnosc Walczaca
      - General
        - General (Folder 15: 6)
        - Bulletins (Folder 15: 7)
      - Program (Folder 15: 8)
      - Zarzad Polityczno Wychowawczy MSW (Folder 15: 9)
  - Political prisoners - Poland - Release of, 1986 (Folder 15: 10)
  - Polityka (Box 16)
    - General (Folder 16: 1)
    - 1956-1980 (Folder 16: 2)
    - 1980-1986 (Folder 16: 3)
  - Polska Zjednoczona Partia Robotnicza
    - General (Folder 16: 4)
    - Corruption (Folder 16: 5)
    - Economic program, 1980s (Folder 16: 6)
    - History, 1944-1951 (Folder 16: 7)
    - Opposition, as viewed by party ideologues (Folder 16: 8)
    - Solidarity as workers movement (Folder 16: 9)
  - Prisoners of conscience., See Amnesty International
  - Propaganda, Communist - Poland - Warsaw (Voivodeship) (Folder 16: 10)
  - Schaff, Adam (Folder 16: 11)
  - Social conflict - Poland (Folder 16: 12)
  - Underground literature - Poland (Box 17)
    - General
      - General
        - General
          - General (Folder 17: 1)
          - 1939-1976 (Folder 17: 2)
          - 1979-1986 (Folder 17: 3)
          - 1982-1987 (Folder 17: 4)
        - Aneks (Folder 17: 5)
        - Niezalezna Oficyna Wydawnicza (Folder 17: 6)
        - Nowa
          - General (Folder 17: 7)
          - Nowa Koalicja, 1987 (Folder 17: 8)
      - Books
        - General
          - 1976-1980 (Folder 18: 1)
          - 1982-1987
            - Part 1 (Folder 18: 2)
            - Part 2 (Folder 18: 3)
            - Part 3 (Folder 18: 4)
        - Bibliography, 1982-1986 (Folder 18: 5)
      - Periodicals (Box 19)
        - General
          - General
            - 1976-1980 (Folder 19: 1-2)
            - 1980-1981 (Folder 19: 3-4)
            - 1982-1987 (Folder 19: 5-7)
          - Analysis of activities, 1987 (Box-folder 20: 1)
          - Bibliographies
            - General, 1982-1987 (Folder 20: 2-3)
            - List, 1985 (Folder 20: 4)
          - Profiles
            - General (Folder 20: 5)
            - 1980-1989 (Folder 20: 6)
          - Samples
            - General (Folder 20: 7)
            - General (Box-folder 21: 1)
            - Educational system
              - General (Folder 21: 2)
              - College youth (Folder 21: 3)
        - Tygodnik Mazowsze (Folder 21: 4)
    - Structure
      - General (Folder 21: 5)
      - List (Folder 21: 6)
  - Urban, Jerzy (Box-folder 22: 1)
  - Wyszynski, Stefan (Folder 22: 2)
  - Youth - Poland
    - General
      - General (Folder 22: 3)
      - 1944-1957 (Folder 22: 4)
    - Western influence (Folder 22: 5)
  - Zielinski, Marek (Folder 22: 6)
  - Zwiazek Harcerstwa Polskiego
    - Émigré (Folder 22: 7)
    - Poland (Folder 22: 8)
- MISCELLANEOUS MATERIALS, 1981-1988 (Box 23)
  - Banknotes printed by political opposition, 1980s (Folder 23: 1)
  - Calendars, 1981-1988 (Folder 23: 2)
  - Cartoons published by the secret police to discredit political opposition, 1980s (Folder 23: 3)
  - Fliers published by various political groups, 1980s (Folder 23: 4)
  - Miniature publications
    - General, 1982-1984 (Folder 23: 5)
    - Sealed packets for delivery by sea (Folder 23: 6)
  - Phonotape cassette covers (Folder 23: 7)
  - Postcards (Folder 23: 8)
- POSTAGE STAMP ALBUMS, 1980-1989 (Box 24)
  - No.1 (Folder 24: 1)
  - No.2 (Folder 24: 2)
  - No.3 (Box-folder 25: 1)
  - No.4 (Folder 25: 2)
  - No.5 (Box-folder 26: 1)
  - No.6 (Folder 26: 2)
  - No.7 (Folder 26: 3)
  - No.8 (Box-folder 27: 1)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1944-1988
  - Bulletins
    - Akademia Spraw Wewnetrznych: Materialy Historyczne
      - 1984 (Folder 27: 2)
      - 1986 (Folder 27: 3)
    - Akademia Spraw Wewnetrznych: Zeszyty Historyczne, 1986 (Folder 27: 4)
    - Akademia Spraw Wewnetrznych: Zeszyty Naukowe (Folder 27: 5)
      - 1974
      - 1988 (Box-folder 28: 1)
    - Departament Szkolenia i Doskonalenia Zawodowego MSW: Sluzba MO, 1981-1983 (Folder 28: 2)
    - Kwartalnik Wyzszej szkoly Oficerskiej im. Feliksa Dzierzynskiego. Problemy Teorii i Praktyki Operacyjnej Sluzby Bezpieczenstwa. Dzialalnosc Grup Antysocjalistycznych w PRL, 1982:1-2 (Folder 28: 3)
    - Zarzad Polityczno - Wychowawczy MSW: Biuletyn Informacyjny, 1987 (Folder 28: 4)
    - Zeszyty Naukowe Wyzszej szkoly Oficerskiej im. Gen. Franciszka Jozwiaka-Witolda, 1977 (Folder 28: 5)
  - Monographs
    - Catholic Church - Legal framework of operations (Folder 28: 6)
    - Criminal law in communist Poland, 1988 (Folder 28: 7)
    - Ideological struggle, 1988 (Folder 28: 8)
    - Illegal meat trade (Box-folder 29: 1)
    - Korpus Bezpieczenstwa Wewnetrzengo (Folder 29: 2)
    - Nowotko, Marceli - Circumstances of his death (Folder 29: 3)
    - NSZZ "Solidarnosc"
      - General (Folder 29: 4)
      - Émigré branches, 1981-1984 (Folder 29: 5)
    - Pacifism (Folder 29: 6)
    - People's militia
      - General
        - 1944-1948 (Folder 29: 7)
        - 1944-1956 (Folder 29: 8)
        - 1944-1984 (Folder 29: 9)
      - Educational role, 1944-1949 (Box-folder 30: 1)
      - Ochotnicza Rezerwa, 1946-1983 (Folder 30: 2)
    - Polish communist party
      - Formation of security forces (Folder 30: 3)
      - Origins (Folder 30: 4)
    - Polish post-war history, 1944-1956
      - Part 1 (Folder 30: 5)
      - Part 2 (Folder 30: 6)
    - Political émigré circles (Box-folder 31: 1)
    - Socialist revolution (Folder 31: 2)
    - Theft of communal property
      - General (Folder 31: 3)
      - Cultural goods, 1946-1977 (Folder 31: 4)
    - Underground organizations
      - German occupation, 1939-1945 (Folder 31: 5)
      - Communist Poland, 1945-1960
        - Part 1 (Folder 31: 6)
        - Part 2 (Box-folder 32: 1)
        - Part 3 (Folder 32: 2)
        - Part 4 (Folder 32: 3)
- VIDEOTAPE CASSETTES, 1980s. (Folder 32: 4)
  Two videotape cassettes issued by NSZZ "Solidarnosc" video services, depicting various social and political events in the 1980s
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1925-1988 (Box 33)
  - 5 prints depicting the release of political prisoners in the city of Wroclaw, 1984 (Folder 33: 1)
  - 36 prints depicting anti-government demonstrations in Lublin, 1982 (Folder 33: 2)
  - 10 prints depicting hunger demonstrations in the city of Lodz, 1981 (Folder 33: 3)
  - 20 prints depicting internees in Bialoleka prison, 1982 (Folder 33: 4)
  - 15 prints depicting religious images painted by the internees in the Uherce prison chapel, 1984 (Folder 33: 5)
  - 1 print depicting Leszek Moczulski, n.d. (Folder 33: 6)
  - 1 print depicting Lech Walesa, n.d. (Folder 33: 7)
  - 20 prints depicting Martial Law in Lodz, 1981 (Folder 33: 8)
  - 4 prints depicting events related to NSZZ "Solidarnosc," 1980-1985 (Folder 33: 9)
  - 20 prints depicting NSZZ "Solidarnosc" activists, 1980s (Folder 33: 10)
  - 63 prints depicting the pilgrimage of workers to the city of Czestochowa, 1988 (Folder 33: 11)
  - 1 print depicting Jozef Pilsudski, n.d. (Folder 33: 12)
  - 8 prints depicting political satire on communist system, 1981 (Folder 33: 13)
  - 11 prints depicting Jerzy Popieluszko as priest, n.d. (Folder 33: 14)
  - 10 prints depicting Jerzy Popieluszko and Lech Walesa participating in a ceremony in Paulines monastery in Czestochowa, 1985 (Folder 33: 15)
  - 34 prints depicting Jerzy Popieluszko's funeral, 1984 (Folder 33: 16)
  - 5 prints depicting Otto Schimek, 1925-1944 (Folder 33: 17)
  - 8 prints depicting wall writings in the city of Krakow, 1983 (Folder 33: 18)
  - 10 prints depicting a NSZZ "Solidarnosc" street blockade in Warsaw, 1981 August (Folder 33: 19)